Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, so that's,
好的，就是，
good afternoon, good morning, good evening, good night,
下午好，早上好，傍晚好，晚上安，
wherever you are,
无论你在哪里，
and I guess welcome to the last week of the semester,
我想欢迎来到本学期的最后一周，
so there's two more class meetings,
所以还有两节课，
today which we're gonna be talking about Blockstack,
今天我们将要讨论的是 Blockstack ，
and on Thursday, we we get a report from a different projects,
周四，我们收到一份来自不同项目的报告，
from the number of the project groups in 6.824.
来自多个 6.824 项目组。
And so, today is basically the last paper discussion.
所以，今天是最后一次论文讨论。
So the topic is,
所以主题是，
you know the system that we're assigned for,
分配给我们的主题，
assigned for reading, which is Blockstack,
分配给我们阅读的，是 Blockstack ，
and really Blockstack that represents is
Blockstack 表示的是，
an approach to building decentralized applications,
一种构建去中心化应用程序的方式，
and with decentralized, what we mean here is that,
对于去中心化，我们这里的意思是，
unlike centralized websites, that sort of website owns the data,
与中心化的网站不同，这个网站拥有数据，
and decentralized application, application,
而去中心化的应用，
the system is set up in a way,
系统以一种方式设置，
that the users actually keep control over the data and not the website.
用户控制数据而不是网站。
So this form sort of a trend, in the last,
这是最后一个[趋势]，
is the final lecture series of three lectures on decentralized distributed systems,
是关于去中心化化分布式系统的三节课的最后一课，
we talk about logs and signing or sign log
我们谈到日志和日志签名，
is a way of constructing this decentralized log storage systems,
是构建这种去中心化的日志存储系统的一种方式，
we saw Bitcoin to see as an example of,
我们看到比特币，作为一个例子，
how you can achieve consensus in decentralized systems
如何在去中心化系统中达成一致，
with untrusted participants or Byzantine participants.
与不信任的参与者或拜占庭参与者。
And so today we're taking one more step up
所以今天我们向前更进一步，
and actually look at how you can actually build complete applications
解如何实际构建完整的应用程序，
other than just crypto currency applications.
而不仅仅是加密货币应用。
The decentralized application has a long history,
去中心化应用有很长的历史，
in the early 2000, late 90s,
在 2000 年早期， 90 年代末，
there was a lot to do around peer-to-peer applications,
有很多点对点应用程序，
which had a decentralized architecture, Napster,
它有一个分散的架构， Napster ，
you know more recently you know probably familiar with Keybase,
最近，你可能对 Keybase 比较熟悉，
which has a decentralized design,
它有一个去中心化的设计，
or Solid,
或者 Solid(https://solidproject.org/) ，
you know and of course Blockstack,
当然还有 Blockstack ，
so there's you know quite a bit of activity,
有相当多的活动，
in this space of decentralized applications.
在这个去中心化应用程序的领域中。
The Blockstack is interesting,
Blockstack 很有趣，
from from the perspective of decentralized applications,
从去中心化应用程序的角度来看，
but also is an example of sort of a non-currency use
但也是一种非货币使用的例子，
non-money use of Bitcoin of the blockchain, the Bitcoin blockchain.
非货币使用比特币区块链。
And we'll see,
我们会看到，
you know there are a number of aspects, that are interesting to Blockstack,
Blockstack 有很多有趣的方面，
but the key thing that the paper focuses on is actually naming,
但这篇论文关注的关键是命名，
how to sort of build a distributed decentralized naming system.
如何在构建一个分布式去中心化命名系统。
And of course the naming systems are widely used,
当然，命名系统也被广泛使用，
you know think of DNS,
想想 DNS ，
think about where you know Kerberos,
想想 Kerberos ，
you know there's tons and tons of different naming systems
有很多不同的命名系统，
out there you know widely used,
它们被广泛使用，
and this is just a different design,
这是一种不同的设计，
where the most interesting part of it, again is it's decentralized.
其中最有趣的部分是，它是去中心化的。
You know this lecture is a little bit different
这节课有一点不同，
than the preceding lectures or many of the preceding lectures,
与许多之前的课，
many preceding lectures sort of have to flavor,
前面的很多课都是，
here's a hard technical problem,
这是一个困难的技术问题，
here's the solution to solve that particular problem,
这是解决这个问题的解决方案，
and here we are in a slightly sort of different position,
这里我们的情况略有不同，
there's a hard technical problem,
有一个困难的技术问题，
that we have to build decentralized applications,
我们必须构建去中心化的应用程序，
but it's not, you know a hundred percent clear,
但是不是，百分百清楚的是，
there's exactly the right thing to do to build decentralized applications
正确构建去中心化应用，
and is extremely [],
是非常[]，
and it's not clear like Blockstack is just the right solution to do so,
还不清楚 Blockstack 是否是正确的解决方案，
and so it's much more experimental,
它更具实验性，
Blockstack does actually have a user community,
Blockstack 有一个用户社区，
and but it's not yet an overwhelming success,
但这还不是压倒性的成功，
and a demonstration that this is a right way to go.
并证明这是一条正确的道路。
So in that sense,
所以，从某种意义上说，
this is a paper in some sense more thought provoking,
这是一篇更发人深省的论文，
than giving actually a definite answer to a particular technical problem.
而不是对一个特定的技术问题给出明确的答案。
And so, some ways you know this is more of topic is sort of,
所以，这个更重要的主题是，
lends ourself to a debate about you know different views on this kind of, kind of design.
让我们参与一场关于这种设计的不同观点的讨论。
So when during lecture,
所以在讲课的时候，
if we get, to be preferred to find actually,
如果我们有，
to have quite a bit of discussion different aspects,
有相当多的讨论不同的方面，
and I don't think there's going to be one right answer.
我认为不会有一个正确的答案。
And so anytime you have a question about
所以，任何时候你有问题，
or what are you about a particular aspect of these decentralized app designs,
或者对这些去中心化应用设计的方面有什么看法，
you know speak up.
你可以说出来。
Okay, so maybe before you know talking about decentralized apps,
好的，也许在讨论去中心化的应用程序之前，
you know just quickly revisit
快速回顾一下，
you know actually what sort of an common paradigm
什么是常见范式，
to actually build websites or build web applications, right.
来构建网站或构建网络应用。
That is really using centralized websites,
这就是使用中心化网站，
sites may itself might be distributed across multiple data centers across the world,
网站可能分布在世界各地的多个数据中心，
but the architecture of the design the site is centralized,
但网站的设计架构是集中式的，
where we have, you know here's typical website,
我们有，这是典型的网站，
it has some applications in the code,
它的代码中有一些应用，
whatever you know Gmail, whatever Twitter Facebook,
无论是 Gmail Twitter Facebook ，
and that operates on a database,
它在数据库上运行，
that contains you know user data.
其中包含用户数据。
Then we might actually has different users
然后我们可能有不同的用户，
interacting with sitting by a web browser and U1, U2,
使用网络浏览器进行交互， U1 U2 ，
they interact through the application to the website,
他们通过应用程序与网站进行交互，
you know they create data, they stored in the database,
他们创建数据，他们存储在数据库中，
other users may view the data,
其他用户可以查看数据，
and the application displays basically that data to inside of the web browser.
应用程序将这些数据显示在网络浏览器中。
And you know the data might be a blog posts, tweets, Piazza posts, photos,
数据可能是博客帖子，推文， Piazza 帖子，照片，
perhaps even more sort of sensitive, medical records, medical records, etc.
也许甚至更敏感的，医疗记录，等等。
And basically you know the application we're running on the site
我们在网站上运行的应用程序，
to transform that data from all the different users,
转换来自所有不同用户的数据，
into something that interesting to look at,
变成一些有趣的东西，
where basically integrating for example the timeline of many users
比如其中集成了许多用户的时间线，
into a single timeline present to the user,
进入一个时间线并展示给用户，
you know we're going to tweets
我们要发表推文，
you know do ups and downloads, etc, etc.
上传和下载，等等。
And you know one sort of distinguishing feature of this design is that,
这个设计的一个显著特点是，
the application of the data are bundled,
数据的应用被捆绑在一起，
they are only the control of the application site,
它们只是由应用程序网站所控制，
whether it's Facebook Twitter or Google or any website,
无论是 Facebook Twitter Google 还是任何网站，
and really the interface between the user
用户之间的界面，
or the dividing line between the user and the website
或者用户和网站之间的分界线，
is basically you know html or the UI,
是 HTML 或 UI ，
and the application basically computes you know whatever a user going to see,
应用程序计算出用户将要看到的内容，
and that's going to be displayed inside the browser,
它将通过浏览器显示，
of course, the application might actually run inside of the browser,
当然，应用程序可能在浏览器内部运行，
you know like Javascript,
比如 Javascript ，
but actually not really pertinent to this particular discussion,
但与这个讨论并不相关，
you know it's still the application is under control of the website,
仍然是应用程序在网站的控制之下，
you know the programmers of the website write the application,
网站的程序员编写应用程序，
and the application basically manipulates the DOM,
应用程序操作 DOM ，
fill from inside of the web browser.
填充到浏览器中。
And so from the user point of view,
所以从用户的角度来看，
interaction, interface you know between the,
交互，界面，
defining interface between website and and the browser still sort of html.
网站和浏览器之间的界面仍然是 HTML 。
And so this kind of design clearly is overwhelmingly successful,
所以这种设计显然是压倒性的成功，
you know most websites probably,
可能大多数网站，
that's probably all of the websites you probably use
可能你使用的所有网站
are sort of following this particular design.
都遵循这种设计。
And one reason for you know this very successful design is,
这个非常成功的设计的一个原因是，
we'll talk a little bit more later is,
我们稍后会讨论，
because of the tight integration between the application and the data
因为应用和数据紧密结合，
and the data from the user,
来自用户的数据，
so the application is easy access to all the user data from different users
应用程序可以轻松访问来自不同用户的所有用户数据，
and integrate it, to make creative and interesting ways.
把它融合在一起，创造出创造性和趣味性的方式。
But there are you know it's not completely perfect, you know this designing,
但这种设计并不是完美的，
sort of things, that you might you might wish could be slightly better.
你可能会希望能做得更好。
And in some sense,
在某种意义上，
decentralized applications is a is a response to those sort of things,
去中心化应用是对这些事情的一种回应，
that not might be one hundred percent desirable.
它可能不是百分百想要的。
And so for one, there's a very simple observation,
所以，首先，有一个非常简单的观察，
you can really not create another application,
你不能创建另一个应用程序，
so the site decides actually how the app looks like,
网站决定了应用程序的外观，
you know that's the UI you're gonna get,
就是你会得到的用户界面，
and which is sort of very different than,
这很不同，
let's see, your own application on your laptop, for example,
比如，你自己笔记本的自己的应用，
you want to modify, edit a text file,
你想修改，编辑一个文本文件，
but you get to choose which browser or editor you're gonna use,
你可以选择要使用的浏览器或编辑器，
you know what are you gonna use Emacs, you know Vim,
你可以使用 Emacs Vim ，
you know all kinds of culture wars
各种各样的文化战争，
about which one is better than the other,
关于哪一个比另一个更好，
but you get an option to choose which one you want to use.
但你有权选择你想要使用哪个。
And in this case, you know that's just not the case,
在这种情况下，情况并非如此，
you're using Gmail,
你使用 Gmail ，
Gmail is not the best example,
Gmail 不是最好的例子，
but Twitter,
但是 Twitter ，
you know Twitter is going to decide actually how the application is going to look like,
Twitter 会决定应用程序的外观，
the reason why Gmail might not be the best example is,
Gmail 可能不是最好的例子的原因是，
because you can actually download your email maybe you know through IMAP,
因为你可以通过 IMAP 下载你的电子邮件，
and then run your own email program,
然后运行自己的电子邮件程序，
but for many websites,
但对于许多网站来说，
you know the user application data very control,
用户应用程序数据非常受控制，
that you have no control over it.
你无法控制它。
The website you know may change the rules on who can see what data,
网站可能会修改谁可以查看哪些数据的规则，
and it might actually do without really telling you,
它可能并没有告诉你，
and so you don't have full control over actually who, who sees your data,
所以你没有完全控制谁能看到你的数据，
furthermore, the website actually might use it, you know your data to generate revenue,
另外，网站可能会使用你的数据产生收入，
whatever decide which ads actually display,
无论是显示哪些广告，
and you know basically snooping over your data, right,
并且窥探你的数据，
or in the worse case, maybe a bad employee,
或者在更糟糕的情况下，可能一个糟糕的员工，
it actually it just snoop over your data.
它窥探你的数据。
And that's really sort of outside of your control,
这在某种程度上是你无法控制的，
there's nothing really you can do about it,
你真的无能为力，
you gave the website the data, it's theirs now.
你把数据给了网站，现在是他们的了。
And so this is sort of sort of pain points,
所以这是一个痛点，
you know it makes people wonder,
这会让人想知道，
you know is a way of designing systems,
是否有一种设计系统的方式，
that are really not, don't follow this paradigm,
它不遵循这种模式，
but follow the paradigm of decentralized applications.
而是遵循去中心化应用程序的模式。
And so in in this world view,
所以在这个世界中，
we're still in our Internet cloud,
我们仍然在互联网中，
but you know we have storage providers,
但我们有存储提供商，
and storage providers are basically nothing really sophisticated word,
存储提供商不是什么真正复杂的词，
they don't really rung app code,
它们并不运行应用程序代码，
they just purely provide storage,
它们只是纯粹地提供存储，
ways of maybe it's like Google drive or whatever or Amazon S3,
比如 Google Drive 或 Amazon S3 等，
but basically they're sort of [] you know big holders,
但它们都是大的持有者，
the data maybe you know users probably want to encrypt data,
可能用户想要加密数据，
but this is what the real goal here is that,
但这才是我们的真正目标，
the user decides you know which store for where the data lives,
用户决定数据所在的存储位置，
and it keeps them under control of the user,
并且使它们处于用户的控制之下，
so whatever you know storage provider,
所以不管什么存储提供商，
S3 might have you know user 1 data,
S3 可能会有用户 1 的数据，
another store provider might actually have U2's data,
另一个供应商可能有 U2 的数据，
or stores you know data [] of U2,
或者保存 U2 的数据，
U2 and user may actually encrypt it,
U2 可能对它进行加密，
so that the storage provider can actually not read it,
使存储提供商不能读取它，
and control like who can actually decrypt the data.
并控制着谁可以对数据进行解密。
And then you know the applications really are in control of the user themselves,
然后应用程序是在用户自己的控制之下，
so you know might user here,
所以这里的用户，
U1 workstation or laptop, it runs an application,
U1 工作站或笔记本，它运行一个应用程序，
and you know here's U2,
这是 U2 ，
there's also another application may actually looking at maybe the same data,
也有另一个应用程序可能查看相同的数据，
but like a slightly different version of the application,
但是一个稍有不同版本的应用程序，
whatever one photo viewer and another photo viewer,
比如一个照片查看器和另一个照片查看器，
and basically to construct you knows what is actually shown to the user,
为了构建显示给用户的是什么，
that the application will fetches data you know from different users,
应用程序将从不同的用户那里获取数据，
for example, U2 share the photos with U1,
例如， U2 与 U1 共享照片，
then the applications to integrate the photos U1 to U2,
然后应用程序整合 U1 U2 的照片，
by extracting or retrieving the, the photos from the different storage providers.
通过从不同存储提供商获取照片。
And here really what the sort of dividing line is between users
在这里，分界线在用户之间，
and the dividing line is is really this,
分界线是这样的，
there's sort of a dividing line between the application and storage,
在应用程序和存储之间有一条分界线，
and so there's a storage API,
所以有一个存储 API ，
you have sort of the uniform,
你有统一的，
because there are many different applications are going to use the same storage API,
因为许多不同的应用程序使用相同的存储[]，
you know maybe this application it creates todo list,
也许这个应用程序创建 todo 列表，
maybe it's a photo list,
可能是一个照片列表，
maybe it's a Twitter clone,
也许这是 Twitter 的克隆，
this retrives tweets from different users
检索来自不同用户的推文，
and integrates them and present them to the user.
并将它们整合在一起呈现给用户。
And it's really that sort of single storage API,
它是一种单一存储 API ，
and that actually provides you know the dividing line
这提供了分界线，
between the applications and the data,
在应用程序和数据之间，
of course, that storage API has to be quite general purpose,
当然，存储 API 必须是非常通用的，
can support multiple applications,
可以支持多个应用程序，
but also has to allow sharing
而且还必须允许共享，
between different, between different users and different applications,
在不同用户和不同应用之间，
the module or the permissions.
模块或权限。
And so let's say you wanted to build sort of you know todo list,
假设你想要建立一个 todo 列表，
then you know between U1 and U2,
在 U1 和 U2 之间，
then let's look at this from the perspective of U1,
我们从 U1 的角度来看，
you know probably there would be some operation
可能会有一些操作
or some sharing operations between U2 and U1,
或在 U2 U1 一些共享操作，
saying like yeah, you know the names of the my todo list,
比如我的 todo list 的名字，
and you know U1 can then download you know the U2's todo list,
U1 可以下载 U2 的 todo 列表，
maybe check you know the signature on the file
也许会检查文件上的签名，
to verify the data was indeed written by U2
来验证数据数据是 U2 写的，
and then you know integrate you know that,
然后整合它，
we have it's own todo list,
我们有自己的 todo 列表，
and present the U1 or share todo list,
展示 U1 或共享 todo 列表，
that contains both U1's and U2's todo items.
包含 U1 和 U2 的 todo 列表。
Sort of sort of the general view
这是一般的角度，
of actually buildings decentralized architecture for applications.
用来构建去中心化架构的应用程序。
Any questions so far?
到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
Okay, so so far,
好的，到目前为止，
we've hopefully received you know
我们希望已经收到了，
this addresses one of the major you know pain point for the centralized approach,
这个集中化方法的主要痛点之一，
that basically the users you know still in control of the data,
用户仍然控制着数据，
it's not owned by a particular site anymore,
它不再属于某个特定的站点，
and users decide who,
用户决定谁，
which applications and who actually get access to data,
哪些应用程序和谁获得数据访问权限。
I think those are desirable property.
我想这是想要的属性。
But you know the this whole design is also with its unique set of challenges,
但是，整个设计也面临着一系列独特的挑战，
and so let me lay out some of them,
所以让我把它们中的一些列出来，
and we'll focus on a few of them in the context of Blockstack.
我们将在 Blockstack 的上下文中重点介绍其中的几个。
And so there's sort of two [] broad categories of challenges,
所以有两大类的挑战，
one sort of on the business side,
一个是商业方面的，
what is the revenue model,
盈利模式是什么，
you know one will get these applications actually being adopted,
有人会让这些应用程序被采用，
and you know pay people money to actually develop the applications,
付钱让人们开发应用程序，
and so they actually become really good,
所以它们变得非常好，
and people are excited by using them.
人们很乐意去使用它们。
I'm not really gonna talk about that at all,
我不想谈这个，
but instead you know what I most focus on the technical challenges.
相反，我最关注的是技术挑战。
And there's several of them,
这里有几个（技术挑战），
one is going to go back to this picture here before,
我们先回来看看这张图片，
you know the storage API sort of the key interface,
存储 API 是关键接口，
and you know interfaces to be minimal,
而且接口是最小的，
and it has to be general purpose enough,
而且它必须是足够通用的，
but in typically, it's actually,
但在通常情况下，它是，
you know it's not the same thing as the API that sits here,
它与这里的 API 不是一回事，
between the application and the database.
在应用程序和数据库之间。
So let's do that, hold on a second.
所以让我们这样做，稍等一下。
Okay, hopefully everyone can seen screen of board again?
好的，希望每个人都能再次看到白板的屏幕？
Good.
好的。
The, so there's a couple of challenges,
所以，有几个挑战，
you know what I was going to point out is,
我要指出的是，
that storage API is typically not as powerful,
存储 API 通常不那么强大，
where that file system API is not as powerful as SQL,
文件系统 API 不如 SQL 强大，
and futhermore, you know not all the data,
此外，并不是所有的数据，
sort of all uses like handy in a single place,
都放在一个地方，
you can run arbitrary queries on,
你可以运行任意查询，
to integrate it in whatever application specific manners.
以任何应用程序的方式集成它。
Yeah, so that's sort of a challenge,
所以这是一种挑战，
that applications rely on the power
应用程序依赖于这种能力，
of being able to run arbitrary queries over all the user data,
能够对所有用户数据任意查询，
that is in decentralized application will be harder to achieve,
这在去中心化应用中更难实现，
because the data is spread out over many maybe different storage servers.
因为数据可能分散在很多不同的存储服务器上。
There's also features that might be harder to implement,
还有一些功能可能更难实现，
like for example if you want implement like eBay,
例如，如果你想实现 eBay ，
then usually have to submit sort of bids,
然后要提交某种出价，
but you know we want to download those bids immediately,
我们想马上下载那些出价，
so there has to be some trusted aspect
所以必须要有某些可信的方面，
to that actually integrates these bids,
来整合了这些出价，
and then decides you know actually who's the winner,
然后决定谁是赢家，
without disclosing those beforehand.
而不会事先透露这些信息。
Similarly, there's challenges around management,
同样，管理方面也存在挑战，
typically these decentralized applications, you know involve crypto keys,
通常，这些去中心化应用涉及加密密钥，
and so, there has to be sort of you know that's often a [] scenario,
所以，这通常是一种[]情景，
some user loses their private key,
一些用户丢失了他们的私钥，
and then you know you can't use your, can't get your data anymore,
然后你不能再得到你的数据了，
and or somebody actually steals your private key
或者有人偷了你的私钥，
and then they can get your data.
然后他们就可以获取你的数据。
So there's a series of technical challenge,
所以有一系列的技术挑战，
you know to make this actually work,
要让这件事真正工作，
and one of them, the one remaining one,
其中一个，剩下的一个，
which is mostly the topic of this lecture is naming.
也是这节课的主题，就是命名。
So sort of broader challenges are basically,
所以，更广泛的挑战是，
I think you know challenge for any sort of decentralized application infrastructure,
我想是对任何类型的去中心化应用基础架构的挑战，
and certainly also in the context of Blockstack,
当然在 Blockstack 的上下文中也是如此，
but in the case of Blockstack,
但是在 Blockstack 情况下，
we're gone mostly you know we'll see actually the importance of names
我们会看到名字的重要性，
and why naming actually is a challenge.
以及为什么命名是一个挑战。
Okay, so before continue,
好的，在继续之前，
I just want to stop here for a second,
我只想在这里停一下，
just sort of give people trying to ask any questions
只是给那些想问任何问题的人，
to contrast sort of these two different ways of building applications,
对比这两种不同的构建应用程序的方式，
whether it's centralized as in sort of traditional model,
无论是像传统模式那样的集中化，
that we're probably all familiar with,
我们可能都很熟悉，
or this decentralized model.
或者这种去中心化的模式。
So what's the challenge exactly with bids?
所以，出价有什么挑战？
So which is the challenge?
挑战是什么呢？
With bids.
通过出价。
Oh, you know you need an,
哦，你需要一个，
application needs to have access to the user bids,
应用程序需要能够访问用户出价，
but shouldn't disclose them, right, to other applications
但不应该将它们透露给其他应用程序，
and so that means that,
这就意味着，
the application that looks like,
应用程序看起来是，
I'm U1, I'm submitting a bid,
我是 U1 ，我提交了出价，
I get U2's bid,
我得到了 U2 的出价，
but my application isn't really to close U2's bid immediately to me,
但我的应用将 U2 的出价直接给我，
because it wouldn't be fair,
因为这不公平，
and so how would you do that,
那么你将如何做到这一点，
so you just perform with a trusted party or whatever some protocol,
所以你需要受信任的一方或任何协议，
that actually makes that happen.
让这一切发生。
Thank you.
谢谢。
If the application runs your models on your workstation,
如果应用程序模型在你的工作站上运行，
you can modify the work, the application, right.
你可以修改应用程序，对吧。
Sorry, in the previous slide, I think you mentioned also,
抱歉，在上一张幻灯片中，我想你也提到了，
app one being different from,
应用 1 不同于，
like the two apps being different,
两个应用是不同的，
what do you mean exactly?
你是什么意思？
Well, example, just made the analogy is very crisp,
好的，举个例子，为了让比喻非常简单，
this could be Vim, this could be Emacs,
这可能是 Vim ，这可能是 Emacs ，
and U1 U2 get to decide
U1 和 U2 可以决定，
which applications are going to use to actually modify their data, right,
使用哪个应用来修改它们的数据，
and you know today in a centralized model,
今天在一个集中化的模式中，
and that not really possible,
这是不可能的，
you know you can't have basically two Twitter apps,
你不可能有两个 Twitter 应用程序，
where U1 one way of interacting with the Twitter app
U1 与 Twitter 应用程序交互的一种方式，
and somebody else you know do it in a different way,
其他人用不同的方式来做，
that's just do Twitter app.
这就是 Twitter 应用程序。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢。
I I had a question just about the design of the decentralized like model,
我有一个问题，关于去中心化模型的设计，
is it necessary for the app to be like a client side
这个应用程序是否需要一个客户端，
or could you know,
或者能不能，
could you have like these like the centralized apps on the Internet sign.
能不能有集中式应用在互联网上的标志。
You can have in principle the Internet,
原则上，你可以在互联网上，
like the key issue,
关键的问题，
it doesn't really have to run on the user's workstation,
它不一定要在用户的工作站上运行，
can run anywhere,
可以在任何地方运行，
but it is on the users control,
但是在用户的控制中，
of course, if somebody writes it,
当然，如果编写它，
but the user gets to decide which app to run over what data.
但用户可以决定运行哪个应用来处理哪些数据。
Right, so the so so the important thing here is, is that,
好的，所以这里最重要的是，
you know app choose you, you should choose the app,
应用选择你，你应该选择应用，
and importantly the app has access to any storage provider.
重要的是，应用程序可以访问任何存储提供商。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Okay, any other questions?
好的，还有其他问题吗？
Okay, so names,
好的，那么名字，
so this is getting a little bit more into Blockstack.
这会更深入了解 Blockstack 。
And then let me sort of layout like the role the names play,
让我来列出命名扮演的角色，
first of all, you have todo list,
首先，你有 todo 列表，
and you want to share it with somebody else,
你想和别人分享它，
you know have to be able to name that user for whom you're sharing,
你必须能够命名要与其共享的用户，
and so there's a sort of mapping from name to user,
所以有一个从名字到用户的映射，
that's an important role,
这是一个重要的角色，
there's mapping for name to location of data.
存在从名字到数据位置的映射。
So if my todo list app,
所以如果我的 todo 列表应用，
share you know todo list of user 1 with user 2,
用户 1 和用户 2 分享 todo 列表，
and then you know what actually retrieve user one want user two's data,
然后，用户 1 想要用户 2 的数据，
there needs to be a way of actually naming user 2 todo list,
需要有一种命名用户 2 的 todo 列表，
and actually retrieving it.
并且获取它。
And then you know there's a certain way,
然后有一种方法，
there's a name to public key mapping,
有一个名字到公钥的映射，
you know when I do you know successfully retrieve user 2 data,
当我成功获取用户 2 的数据，
you know probably want to verify it, actually was written by user 2,
可能想要验证它，是由用户 2 编写的，
and so probably user 2's public key to verify the integrity of the data retrieved,
因此可能使用用户 2 的公钥来验证获取的数据的完整性，
because the storage providers might be, can then be untrusted,
因为存储提供商可能不是可信任的，
and that requires that,
这就要求，
I can establish what actually user 2's public key is in a reliable manner.
我能够以可靠的方式确定用户 2 的公钥。
And so you should think about
所以，你应该考虑到，
in every step of these decentralized applications,
在这些去中心化的应用程序的每一步中，
you know the name plays a crucial role.
名字起着至关重要的作用。
And and the common name given
通用的名称给出
the particular for you know the mapping from names to keys,
从名称到密钥的映射，
which is a crucial keys
至关重要的密钥，
is to be called public key infrastructure.
称为公钥基础设施。
And that is you know building actually any public key infrastructure is quite challenging,
构建任何公钥基础设施都是相当具有挑战性的，
you know you might be familiar like DNSSec,
你可能对 DNSSec 很熟悉，
there's are a particular way of course on the world wide web has,
在万维网上有一种特殊的方式，
certificate has a whole public key infrastructure,
证书具有完整的公钥基础设施，
Kerberos you know an example of public key infrastructure,
Kerberos 是公钥基础设施的一个示例，
and in some ways,
在某些方面，这个论文，
with you know this paper actually do is
这篇论文所做的是，
you will get another public infrastructure,
你将获得另一个公共基础设施，
that is completely decentralized.
这是完全去中心化的。
And that's sort of a key aspect,
这是一个关键的方面，
you know what interesting about this naming scheme in the, in blockstack,
Blockstack 中命名方案有趣的地方，
that's actually provides decentralized public key infrastructure.
这提供了去中心化的公钥基础设施。
Let me try to explain a little bit why this is challenging,
让我试着解释一下，为什么这是具有挑战性的，
so, the paper refers to this in a couple places,
论文在几个地方提到了这一点，
and says like you know there's, there's three aspects that you want,
有三个方面是你想要的，
if you want a general purpose for naming infrastructure,
如果你想要一个一般目的的命名基础设施，
you want to be able to have unique names,
你想要有唯一的名字，
you know have a unique name for every user,
每个用户都有一个唯一的名字，
so that you can identify
这样你就可以识别
you know the particular John or particular Joe, you're talking about that.
你所说的那个 John 或那个 Joe 。
Human human readable names,
人类可读的名字，
so it's easy to remember.
所以可以很容易记住。
And then in this case,
在这种情况下，
what Blockstack also wants is decentralized.
Blockstack 也想要的是去中心化。
And you know the paper sort of makes the point that,
这篇论文的观点是，
it's easy to get two of the three,
很容易能得到三个中的两个，
it's very difficult to get all three of them,
但是很难得到全部三个，
and you know maybe,
也许，
let's look at a couple naming systems,
让我们来看看几个命名系统，
to see which two they do get.
看看他们得到了哪两个。
So let's think about like email addresses.
让我们来考虑一下电子邮件地址。
Okay, email addresses, are they unique names?
好的，电子邮件地址，它们是唯一的名字吗？
Yes.
是的。
Are they human readable?
它们是人类可读的吗？
Yeah.
它们是去中心化的吗？
No.
不是。
No, so this get two of these guys, correct,
不，所以这个得到这两个，
but not the third one.
但没有第三个。
How about random public keys,
随机公钥怎么样，
or maybe like the paper uses hash of the file contents
或者论文使用文件内容的哈希值，
to actually get a name, correct, for the [],
来获取[]的名字，
so basically okay so random public keys,
所以，随机的公钥，
which means public keys get random,
意味着公钥是随机的，
so public keys, are they unique?
那么公钥，它们是唯一的吗？
Yep.
是的。
Yep, are they human readable?
是的，它们是人类可读的吗？
No.
不是。
No, are they decentralized?
不，它们是去中心化的吗？
Yes.
是的。
Yeah yeah, you can generate them
是的，你可以生成它们，
high probability in a unique manner completely decentralized.
以一种独特的、完全去中心化的方式。
So in fact, you sort of done that more in lab 3 with these clerk ids,
事实上，你在实验 3 中用这个生成 clerk id ，
so here we got, like we got two of the three,
所以我们得到了三个中的两个，
but not the human readable one.
但没有人类可读的那个。
Let's see, can we actually get human readable and decentralized?
让我们来看看，我们能获得人类可读和去中心化吗？
Can you think of an example?
你能想出一个例子吗？
Is it like a peer to peer file sharing?
这是不是比如点对点文件共享？
Yeah.
嗯。
It not unique, the files,
这些文件不是唯一的，
but they're human readable and decentralized.
但它们是人类可读的，而且是去中心化的。
Yeah, think simpler,
是的，想得简单一点，
you know think about your phone,
想想你的手机，
the example for me always is a good one,
对我来说，这个例子是很好的，
it looks like your contact list,
看看你的联系人列表，
the names of your contact human readable you know implies,
你的联系人的名字是人类可读的，
you know you could have John,
你可以有 John ，
you know the entry for John one phone number,
John 的条目有一个手机号，
and I can have another phone number or my John entry,
我可以在我的 John 条目有另一个手机号码，
they're probably different people,
他们可能是不同的人，
but you know I can pick the names in decentralized manner,
但我可以以去中心化的的方式选择名字，
and they're certainly readable,
而且它们当然是可读的，
are they unique?
它们是唯一的吗？
No, correct,
不是，
this is like you have your list of names,
你有你的名字列表，
I have my list of names,
我有我的名字列表，
and they may actually overlap,
它们可能会重叠，
and still talk about different people.
仍然谈论不同的人。
So here's sort of what the paper trying to get at,
所以这是论文试图得到的东西，
actually getting two out of three,
实际上是三个中的两个，
you know it's quite common or actually easy,
这很常见，或者很容易，
but actually getting all three of them is hard.
但是获取所有三个，很难做到。
And in the paper, so it's like,
在论文中，它就像，
well, we actually, we achieve all three of them,
我们实现了这三个目标，
then we get the unique names, user readable and decentralized.
我们得到唯一的名称，用户可读的和去中心化的。
And in the way, in some ways they they get this is
他们得到这个的方法是，
basically exploited blockchain.
利用区块链。
So Blockstack approach,
所以 Blockstack 方法，
and really [] they be fair,
而且[]他们是公平的，
it's really not Blockstack approaches,
这实际上不叫 Blockstack 方式，
really namecoins approach, that they sort of adopted.
他们采用的是 namecoins 方法。
The basic idea is very simple,
基本的想法很简单，
we're going to take advantage
我们将利用这个优势，
of the existence of the Bitcoin blockstack, with Bitcoin blockchain
比特币区块区块链的存在，
and of course you can use any other blockchain,
当然，你也可以使用任何其他的区块链，
but like just for concreteness,
但只是为了具体，
we're going to think about the Bitcoin one.
我们考虑比特币的。
And so here we got our chain,
所以这里有我们的链，
you know transactions that in Bitcoin,
在比特币中的交易，
and you know grows over time,
随着时间的推移，
you know miners add new transactions,
矿工增加了新的交易，
and the way we're gonna basically create naming system is,
我们要创建命名系统的方法是，
we're going to just post transactions that sort of different type,
我们将发布不同类型的交易，
they basically claim a name.
他们都自称一个名字。
And so, for example you know we might actually have special transactions,
例如，我们可能有特殊的交易，
because every transaction actually turns out in Bitcoin has a metadata field,
因为比特币中的每一笔交易都有一个元数据字段，
that you can basically stick anything in the metadata fields you want,
你可以将任何内容放入到元数据字段中，
and so what we're going to stick in there is a name record.
所以我们要放入的是一个名字记录。
So we're gonna have some transaction,
所以我们要做一些交易，
and then we're going to take a name record in there,
然后我们在那里记下名字记录，
you'll see a little in the second,
你稍后会看到，
but exactly the details of this name record is,
但是这个名字记录的细节是，
but in the case of Blockstack,
但在 Blockstack 的情况下，
you know it's basically a name like 6.824,
它基本上是一个像 6.824 这样的名字，
and then maybe as we see later,
然后，也许正如我们稍后看到的，
a hash of the zone file.
一个区域文件的哈希值。
And you know the basic rule in the in this scheme is going to be that,
在这个方案中的基本规则是，
the first one, the first user, first name record basically wins, right,
第一个用户，第一个名字记录会赢，
so there might be a second,
所以稍后可能，
you know somebody else creates in the name 6.824 later,
有其他人创造了名字 6.824 ，
but because you know the 6.824 shows up later in
但因为 6.824 出现较晚，
or in the Bitcoin blockchain,
在比特币区块链中，
we're gonna basically ignore that one,
我们会忽略这一点，
and you know only you know consider that valid name record for 6.824,
只考虑有效的 6.824 名字记录，
and this completely you know plays off on the fact,
这完全是基于这样一个事实，
that there's basically blockchain is a log of all the operations ever happened,
区块链是所有发生过的操作的日志，
they're in order, they're consensus,
它们是有序的，它们是有共识的，
in what order they happened,
以它们发生的顺序，
and so from that,
从这个开始，
we've been basically construct, if you will, like a database,
我们已经构建了一个类似数据库，
a database with all the names in the order,
一个按顺序列出所有名字的数据库，
you know just go through the blockchain from beginning of time,
从一开始就通过区块链，
find the valid transactions, name transactions,
查找有效的交易，名字交易，
and use that to construct database with all the, with all the valid names.
并使用它来构建所有有效名称的数据库。
In some ways, a number number of people sort of pointed this out,
在某些方面，一些人指出了这一点，
like isn't this exactly what we've been doing lab 3,
这不正是我们实验 3 所做的吗，
where you know we have log, like Raft provides to log,
我们有日志， Raft 提供了日志，
we stick up operations in the log,
我们把操作记录在日志里，
you know we run you know the operations,
我们执行操作，
and that constructs you know the state,
这构建了状态，
where the state in this case would be a naming database,
状态在这种情况下将是命名数据库，
and there's you know, I think it's exactly that kind of style,
我认为这是那种风格，
in the same idea, except the small differences here,
相同的想法，除了这里的微小区别，
we're not using Raft to get the consensus,
我们不是使用 Raft 获得共识，
we're again using Bitcoin or Nakamoto or to get to Nakamoto consensus
我们再次使用比特币或中本聪共识，
to actually achieve one single blockchain.
实现一个区块链。
But in spirit, you know, yes you know it's very similar.
但在本质上，是的，这非常相似。
Okay, so let's think a little bit about it,
好的，让我们想一想，
you know our three properties,
我们的三个属性，
you know first of all, you know, do we do get unique names?
首先，我们有唯一的名字吗？
Yes.
是的。
Yeah, we got to unique names, correct,
是的，我们有唯一的名字，
because the first one wins.
因为第一个会赢。
Is it decentralized?
它是去中心化的吗？
Yes.
是的。
Yeah, decentralized by sort of Bitcoin, right,
是的，按比特币的方式去中心化，
and the consensus and the log basically makes sure that,
共识和日志确保了，
we can actually identify what the first name is,
我们可以确定第一个名字是什么，
so that we can actually pick a unique name.
我们就可以选择一个唯一的名字。
Is it human readable?
它是人类可读的吗？
Can be.
可以的。
Yeah, exactly, yeah,
是的，没错，是的，
certainly, my stream 6.824 hopefully user readable.
当然，我的[流] 6.824 是用户可读的。
Okay, so it seems like it's sort of first brought you know three,
好的，所以它看起来第一次带来了三个，
you know it looks like indeed you know we got the three properties, right,
看起来我们得到了三个属性，
we got user readable, we got the uniqueness, we got decentralized.
我们有用户可读，我们有唯一性，我们有去中心化。
And I think that really Namecoin was sort of the first naming system
我想 Namecoin 是第一个命名系统，
demonstrated that could be that could be achieved in this way.
证明了可以通过这种方式实现。
Now, it's not completely perfect, right,
现在，它并不是完美的，
like for example even though we got sort of unique names and user readable,
例如，即使我们有一些唯一的名称和用户可读的，
we don't really know like what 6.824 really means, correct,
我们不知道 6.824 到底是什么意思，
6.824 and what does 6.824 refer to,
6.824 ， 6.824 指的是什么，
is like a a part number,
是一个章节编号，
or is it a class number or anything,
或者是班级编号或其他什么，
we don't really know how interpret names,
我们不知道如何解释名字，
but you know they still human readable,
但它们仍然是人类可读的，
its not completely perfect,
它不是完美的，
it's not identifying uniquely some user in the world, right,
它不是唯一地识别世界上的某个用户，
and even like whatever you were done [],
甚至就像你执行[]，
that doesn't really uniquely identify one person, right,
这并不能唯一地识别一个人，
so whenever you see a name,
所以当你看到一个名字的时候，
there's still the issue of like who it actually really is.
仍然有一个问题，比如它到底是谁。
And also, there's sort of a similar you know related issue,
另外，还有一个类似的相关问题，
why it's not completely perfect,
为什么它不是完美的，
which is like,
这就像是，
how, how do you find somebody's name,
你怎么找到某人的名字，
and you know how do you find actually you know what [] name,
你如何找到[]名字，
how do and how do you find that,
你如何找到它，
how do you know which record actually goes with, which particular user,
你如何知道哪条记录与哪个用户匹配，
so although although the system is quite cool,
所以虽然这个系统很酷，
because it has these decentralized, unique and human readable aspects to it,
因为它有这些去中心化的，唯一的和人类可读的方面，
you know it's not completely perfect,
这并不是完美的，
and these are generally issues with general naming systems,
这些是通用命名系统的问题，
but certainly true here too,
但在这里也是如此，
so it's not the case that,
所以不是这种情况，
you know we we should have solved all naming problems,
我们应该解决所有的命名问题，
in one single swoop,
一气呵成，
we do have a good good standing position to work with,
我们有很好的立足点可以合作，
but it's not completely hundred percent hit.
但这并不是百分之百成功。
So question, so Namecoin,
所以，问题，所以， Namecoin ，
all they did was add essentially this record to the the like transaction?
他们所做的是将这条记录添加到交易中？
Well, I think we did a little bit more, correct,
嗯，我想我们做得更多，
they run their own blockchain, independent of Bitcoin,
他们运行自己的区块链，独立于比特币，
and used blockchain, there purely for many,
使用区块链，有很多，
and they had also a bunch of rules about,
他们还有一系列的规则，
like how much money, how many namecoins you have to pay
比如，你要付多少 Namecoin ，
to get a particular name,
来得到特定的名字，
and there's all kinds of other extensions,
还有各种各样的其他扩展，
that I really discussed yet were mentioned,
我还没有提到，
but they sort of followed this particular approach,
但他们遵循了这种方法，
and were the first to do so,
是第一个这样做的，
in many pragmatic issues paper touches on,
在论文涉及的许多务实问题中，
when I haven't mentioned at all yet.
我还没有提到。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Okay, so let's actually dive in a little bit on the sort of the practical issues,
好的，让我们稍微深入到一些实际问题上，
although there's a slightly different nature,
尽管性质略有不同，
we want to we just talked about,
我们想要讨论，
it really is by the,
它是通过，
how to actually implement decentralized apps and naming system,
如何实现去中心化的应用程序和命名系统，
by leveraging Bitcoin.
通过利用比特币。
And there's a bunch of, a bunch of very short just pragmatic issues,
这里有一些很简单的务实问题，
there are limits on the amount of data,
数据量是有限制的，
you can put in on data size in a transaction.
你可以在交易中放的数据大小。
So, although maybe it's perfectly fine to have a name,
所以，尽管也许有个名字是很好的，
value binding into the, into the, into the Bitcoin transaction,
值绑定进入比特币交易，
and we can't put our todo list inside of that transaction,
我们不能把我们的 todo 列表放在那笔交易中，
and so you know we've got to have some plan,
所以我们得有个方案，
if we're actually how that part is going to work out.
这部分是如何工作的。
It has slow writes,
它的写入速度很慢，
we know from the last lecture,
我们从上一节课上知道，
it takes a while for write actually or transactions to propagate,
它需要一段时间写入交易传播，
and before they decided to be really stable,
在它们决定稳定之前，
it cannot be forked off anymore,
它不能再分叉，
you know we might be talking about like you know four five six blocks later in the chain,
我们谈论的可能是链后面的四五六个区块，
you know any blocks ten minutes,
每个区块 10 分钟，
so you know an hour later, right,
所以是一小时之后，
and so it's really not so cool,
所以这不是很酷，
if we're stick our todo list inside of the blockchain too,
如果我们也将 todo 列表放在区块链内部，
because you know I modify my block, my chain, I modify my todo list,
因为我修改我的区块链，修改我的 todo 列表，
you know like an hour later, maybe actually observe it,
大概一个小时后，也许观察到了它，
so that seems not so good,
所以这看起来不太好，
and you want to go to more aggressive applications,
你想要更积极的应用程序，
where there's much more data that's manipulated,
有更多的数据需要操作，
you know certainly a problem,
当然是一个问题，
in a similar, in addition are slow, right,
类似的，除了慢，
so there's also low throughput, low bandwidth,
还有慢吞吐量，慢带宽，
in the [], there's only a few transactions per second, correct,
在[]中，每秒只有几笔交易，
so we're gonna do a lot of writes you know to file,
我们有很多写入到文件中，
and many times we're also,
很多时候，我们也，
we're going running the file operations through blockchain,
我们将通过区块链运行文件操作，
so, so clearly you know we've got to be a little bit,
所以，很明显，我们必须要有一点，
if we want to really build a general purpose infrastructure for decentralized applications,
如果我们想为去中心化的应用程序构建通用的基础设施，
it's going to be a more complete story,
将是一个更完整的故事，
that actually allows us to get like fast writes,
这允许我们得到快速的写入，
you know high bandwidth writes,
高带宽写入，
and gets around you know basically not running everything in the blockchain.
不在区块链中运行所有东西。
The paper also talks about one other final problem,
这篇论文还讨论了另一个最后的问题，
the ledger, ever growing ledger,
账本，[增长]账本，
I'm not actually spend much time about talking about that at all,
我不会花太多时间来谈论这一点，
but it's going to also issue,
但它也会发出，
if you want to do, as [] in the paper,
如果你，[]在论文中，
you are going to boot up a Blockstack node,
你将启动一个 Blockstack 节点，
if you do sort of a traditional Bitcoin style,
如果你采用传统的比特币风格，
where you're gonna run through all the transactions one by one,
你要逐一检查所有的交易，
that will take a while,
这将需要一段时间，
before you actually build up a complete naming record,
才能建立起完整的命名记录，
in particular, in the case of Blockstack is a little bit annoying,
特别是，在 Blockstack 的情况下有点烦人，
because a lot of the transactions that are in the blockchain
因为区块链中的很多交易
are completely irrelevant to Blockstack, right,
与 Blockstack 完全无关，
there there whatever transaction is actually a completely different purpose,
在那里，交易是一个完全不同的目的，
and have nothing to do with Blockstack approach,
与 Blockstack 方法无关，
you know Blockstack,
Blockstack ，
if you literally using the Bitcoin blockchain as your fundamental thing,
如果你使用比特币区块链作为你的基础，
you would have to go through an interpreter
你必须通过一个解释器，
and see which ones actually going to apply.
看看哪些会应用。
Okay, so we're going to focus more on some of these first couple of challenges,
好的，我们将更多地关注前几个挑战，
which is like you know basically what we wanna do is
我们想做的是，
minimized the use of blockchain,
最大限度地减少区块链的使用，
you know so we get high performance writes or [].
所以我们可以获得高性能写入或[]。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Good, that's what gets you the core of the paper,
好的，这就是这个论文的核心，
which is like,
也就是，
we pull up the diagram,
让我们调出图，
so we can look at it,
这样我们就能看到它了，
that's basically this diagram.
就是这张图。
And that sort of description of the general approach,
这是对一般方法的描述，
the paper takes to address the challenges,
这篇论文应对这个挑战，
that I just laid out on the previous board.
我刚刚在上一块白板上展示的。
Okay, so this is a complicated picture
好的，这是一张复杂的图，
and so let's go for layer by layer,
所以让我们一层一层地看，
and try to understand actually how things work.
试着了解事情是如何工作的。
So at the bottom,
所以在底部，
here is the, you know is the Bitcoin chain,
这是比特币链，
and in in the Bitcoin chain, there's a lot of transactions,
在比特币链中，有很多交易，
and many of these transactions have absolutely nothing to do with Blockstack, right.
而这些交易中的许多与 Blockstack 完全没有任何关系。
Write down Blockstack here.
在这里写下 Blockstack 。
And the Blockstack transactions are sort of sitting in
Blockstack 位于
you know a particular blocks in the blockchain,
区块链中的特定区块，
and then there's a second layer,
然后这是第二层，
which really is the Blockstack nodes,
也就是 Blockstack 节点，
that basically read all these transactions,
它们读取了所有这些交易，
fish out the ones that are actually related to Blockstack,
找出那些与 Blockstack 相关的，
interpret those operations
解释这些操作，
and you know build up a Blockstack database with names
构建一个带有名称的 Blockstack 数据库
to what turns out to be zone file hashes.
转换为区域文件哈希值。
So we look at these operations,
所以我们看看这些操作，
when the ones in there,
这里面的，
so in every Bitcoin transactions,
所以在每一个比特币交易中，
as I mentioned early, you can have some metadata,
正如我之前所说的，你可以有一些元数据，
that's in the what's called the OP_RETURN field,
在所谓的 OP_RETRUN 字段，
and in the OP_RETRUN field,
在 OP_RETURN 字段中，
there's basically a name, say x plus you know the hash of zone file,
有一个名字，比如 x 加上区域文件的哈希值，
and that's sort of the binding, that sits in a Bitcoin,
这是某种绑定，位于比特币中，
and basically Blockstack that uses Bitcoin
Blockstack 使用比特币，
to basically make that binding from from name to zone file unique,
使从名称到区域文件的绑定是唯一的，
and in a decentralized manner.
并以一种去中心化的方式。
So as, you know, like in lab 3 or in any other sort of logging system,
所以，像在实验 3 或任何其他类型的记录系统中一样，
the Blockstack nodes interpret these particular name transactions,
Blockstack 节点解释这些特定的名称交易，
look at OP field,
查看 OP 字段，
see that this OP field,
看到这个 OP 字段，
is for example to create a particular name,
例如创建了一个特定的名称，
and basically store in the database,
并存储在数据库中，
the binding from name x you know to the hash of the zone file,
从名称 x 到区域文件哈希的绑定，
and once a while, as we've seen in the second,
一旦，我们稍后会看到，
usually want to update zone file,
通常想要更新区域文件，
so you might see multiple transactions for the zone,
你可能会看到 zone 的多个交易，
user updating basically hash the zonefile.
用户更新那个 zonefile 的哈希值。
Of course, we want to minimize you know these changes,
当然，我们希望最大限度地减少这些变化，
because every change to the, would require,
因为每一次更改都需要，
would require modification or posting a Bitcoin transaction,
需要修改或发布比特币交易，
and you know for many reasons on the previous slide, that's slow,
在上一张幻灯片中，由于许多原因，这是很慢的，
which would like to try to avoid it,
应该尽量避免它，
futhermore, it will cost a little bit of money,
而且，这会花费一些钱，
I mean, there's these transactions need to be a process.
我的意思是，这些交易需要一个过程。
And so, so the basic plan,
所以基本的方案，
so this this node layer, virtual chain layer,
所以这个节点层，虚拟链层，
basically built this database of mapping from name to hash zonefile,
建立了从名称到 zonefile 哈希的映射数据库，
you know of course also filters out all the transactions that are invalid
当然，还可以过滤掉所有无效的交易，
or like you know new x are being created after the first one.
或者，新的 x 在第一个之后被创造出来。
And then, using the hash at the zonefile,
然后，使用 zonefile 的哈希，
you know which we got,
我们得到的，
it locates, an application could locate the zonefile,
应用程序可以定位 zonefile ，
and the zonefile can come from anywhere,
并且 zonefile 可以来自任何地方，
and because we have to hash with the zonefile,
因为我们必须对 zonefile 进行哈希，
when we retrieve a file that claims to be the zonefile,
当我们收到一个声称是 zonefile 的文件时，
we can re-compute the hash,
我们可以重新计算哈希，
if the hash is identical to the one that we got through interactive through Bitcoin,
如果哈希与我们通过比特币交互获得的哈希相同，
then we know for sure, that is the zonefile that goes with x.
那么我们可以确定，这就是与 x 对应的 zonefile 。
So, okay, what is that in a zonefiles,
所以， zonefile 里是什么，
well, in zonefile is for yet another table,
在 zonefile 中是另一张表，
if you will, of mapping names to URIs,
是名字到 URI 的映射，
so for example, you might have a zonefile,
例如，你可能有一个 zonefile ，
which has like maybe for a todo app,
它可能是一个 todo 应用程序，
that's an entry todo, and thit points to a URI,
这是一个 todo 条目，它指向一个 URI ，
where actually the data is located for you know todo list.
todo 列表数据位于这里。
And there's sort of two types of zonefiles,
这里有两种类型的 zonefile ，
and one is what's called is mutable and one is immutable,
一个是可变的，一个是不变的，
the mutable ones have URI plus a public key,
可变的具有 URI 和公钥，
so, and this is public key,
所以，这是公钥，
is the key to actually validate,
是用来验证的密钥，
whether whether the file was written by the user x,
文件是否由用户 x 写入，
so basically the user x you know publishes through this zonefile,
所以用户 x 通过这个 zonefile 发布，
public key for him or herself,
他或她自己的公钥，
and later on, when user 2 want to look up user x,
稍后，当用户 2 想要查找用户 x 时，
you know gets the hash at the zonefile,
从 zonefile 中得到哈希值，
the hash finds the zonefile, double checks that the zonefile,
哈希查找 zonefile ，检查 zonefile ，
you know hash is to the right value,
哈希值是正确的，
looks inside the zonefile,
查看 zonefile 内部，
finds the you know the public key of x
查找的 x 的公钥，
and the URI you know for the todo file,
以及 todo 文件的 URI ，
usually the URI to fetch the actual todo file,
通常 URI 来获取真正的 todo 文件，
check you know the signature on the receive file with the public key,
使用公钥检查获取文件的签名，
and it all checks out,
所有都检查了，
then basically user 2 knows,
然后用户 2 知道，
you know I got you know user x zonefile.
我得到了用户 x 的 zonefile 。
And then it might be also like other names in this zonefile,
然后可能像 zonefile 中的其他名字，
like whatever user access tweets, etc, timeline whatever,
无论用户访问推文，还是时间线，等等，
you know for every application is probably an entry,
对于每个应用程序可能都是一个条目，
and you know probably the applications sort agree on
应用程序可能会达成一致，
like one name to use for a particular application.
比如一个名称用于特定的应用程序。
So don't we lose the like data immutability guarantees,
我们不会失去数据的不变性保证，
where it's possible this data could be deleted,
这些数据可能会被删除，
and then you wouldn't have the hash of data, could be lost.
然后你就不会有数据的哈希值，可能会丢失。
So what do you mean, like the zonefile get lost?
你是什么意思， zonefile 丢失吗？
Right, like like with the chain, you can't lose data,
是的，在链中，你不能丢失数据，
because it'll be replicated enough places,
因为它会被复制到足够多的地方，
but here, that's not to guaranteed.
但在这里，这不是被保证的。
So, turns out zonefiles also replicated widely,
所以， zonefile 也被广泛复制，
on basically there's a core in a Blockstack,
在 Blockstack 的核心，
all replicated a zonefiles to everybody,
复制了 zonefile 给每个人，
and the zonefile reasonable small,
zonefile 是很小的，
like for kilobyte or something in that order,
例如千字节或什么，
and so they can be replicated everywhere,
所以它们可以被复制到任何地方，
okay?
好的？
Then for the todo list, todo file URI,
然后对于 todo 列表， todo 文件 URI ，
the basic idea is that,
基本的想法是，
you might store the same data at multiple providers,
你可以将相同的数据存储在多个提供商中，
for example you might want to have replicated it S3,
例如，你可能希望将其复制到 S3 ，
and maybe you also stick it in Google Drive,
也许你也会把它放在 Google Drive 上，
and one reason that actually Blockstack that has storage servers is,
Blockstack 拥有存储服务器的一个原因是，
not because actually they store data,
不是因为它们存储数据，
but basically providing uniform API to all these different storage providers.
而是为所有这些不同的存储提供商提供统一的 API 。
Okay, so there.
好的，就是这样。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Okay, so there's a, I mentioned zonefiles in two ways,
好的，我提到 zonefile 有两种方式，
there's another which are called immutable storage,
还有一种称为不可变存储，
and that actually contains the URI, name,
它包含了 URI 、名称 ，
URI, public key, and the hash of the data of the file.
URI 、公钥和文件数据的哈希值。
So you can basically verify,
所以你可以检查，
you know, is this indeed the latest version of the file,
这是否是文件的最新版本，
because in this scheme, you get to update,
因为在这个方案中，你可以更新，
you know x can update the file,
x 可以更新文件，
but it's hard to tell, for user 2,
但对用户 2 来说，很难区分，
whether that is actually the latest version,
这是不是最新版本，
the paper mentions that,
这篇论文提到，
there you know probably the version numbers in it,
可能版本号在其中，
but if you really want to guarantee to be sort of latest version for a particular name,
但如果你想保证是某个名字的最新版本，
if you're using immutable storage,
如果使用的是不可变存储，
you know then, the immutable storage contains the hash of the file,
不变的存储包含文件的哈希，
and that uniquely identifies a particular version of that particular file.
它唯一地标识特定文件的特定版本。
That does mean, like if you update this record,
这意味着，如果你更新这个记录，
then, that really means you update the zonefile,
然后，这意味着你更新 zonefile ，
so that means,
这意味着，
you have to republish or re-create a log entry in the Bitcoin chain,
你必须在比特币链中重新发布或重新创建一个日志条目，
mapping you know x to a new a hash hash zonefile.
将 x 映射到一个新的哈希 zonefile 。
Okay, so this is the overall picture for for the system,
好的，这就是这个系统的总体情况，
and as you can see,
正如你所看到的，
you know particular like you know use todo list site,
使用 todo 列表网站，
you know the user x can actually update it's is todo list,
用户 x 可以更新它的 todo 列表，
without actually having to publish a new record in the in the Bitcoin chain,
不必在比特币链中发布新的记录，
in fact, the only thing that really has to be created in the Bitcoin chain is
事实上，比特币链条中唯一需要创造的东西是
just you know x's name,
只有 x 的名字，
and x of course might have many other names,
当然， x 可能还有很多其他的名字，
that are sitting in the zonefiles,
它们位于 zonefile 中，
in, and but you know the the,
但是你知道，
this system doesn't rely on for every operation on the, on the blockchain,
这个系统并不依赖于区块链上的每个操作，
which gets around, gets around a lot of these problems
它绕过了许多这样的问题，
of slow rates, low bandwidth,
如低速率、低带宽，
and the limits of that,
以及限制，
and limits on the on the data that actually appear in a transaction record,
以及对交易记录中出现的数据的限制，
because the only data really has to appear in this transaction record,
因为只有数据必须出现在交易记录中，
is this name plus the hash of the zonefile.
就是这个名字加上 zonefile 的哈希值。
Sorry, how can we find the zonefile, if you only have the hash.
抱歉，我们如何找到 zonefile ，如果只有哈希值？
It's a very good question,
这是一个非常好的问题，
we don't really care, where it comes from,
我们并不关心，它来自哪里，
and so you know they call this the routing layer,
所以他们把这叫做路由层，
basically you tell the routing layer,
基本上，你告诉路由层，
hey, I'm looking for a file that has the following hash,
嘿，我在找一个具有以下哈希值的文件，
and then the routing layer has to produce that file,
然后路由层会产生那个文件，
and you can check whether you got the right file,
你可以检查是否获得了正确的文件，
like re-computing the hash
通过重新计算哈希，
and see you match the one that you're asking for.
看看是不是你要的那个。
Any other questions about this?
对于这个，还有其他问题吗？
So sorry, just to clarify,
抱歉，只是为了确认一下，
operations within this file storage or the zonefiles
文件存储或 zonefile 中的操作
is still limited by the underlying blockchain though, right?
仍然受到底层区块链的限制，对吗？
Yes or no, what are you thinking?
是或不是，你是怎么想的？
Or just like, because modifications or changes to like the file will need a new hash,
或者因为对文件的修改或更改需要新的哈希，
and therefore a new log entry within the blockchain,
因此在区块链内形成新的日志条目，
so you still have to wait for that to be quote unquote accepted,
所以你仍然需要等待“被接受”，
which is like an hour, right.
大概是一个小时，对吧。
Yeah, though, absolutely true,
是的，没错，
so when you make a change to the zonefile,
当你对 zonefile 进行更改时，
that has to run through the txn,
它必须通过 txn ，
for example updating todo list,
例如更新 todo 列表，
wouldn't have to require a Bitcoin transaction,
不需要比特币交易，
you don't really update the zonefile at all,
你根本没有更新 zonefile ，
you know you're just updating todo list file,
你只是更新 todo 列表文件，
and the zonefile only contains the name todo and URI plus the public key,
zonefile 只包含 todo 的名字、 URI 和公钥，
but you're not updating any of those.
但你没有更新其中的任何一个。
I see, but doesn't, don't we store also the hash of the file,
我明白了，但是我们不是也存储文件的哈希值吗，
so if we change the content.
如果我们改变内容。
That's only,
这只是，
there are two cases,
有两种情况，
there's a mutable storage and immutable storage,
有可变的存储和不变的存储，
and what they propose is that,
他们提出的是，
for immutable storage like storage, you don't update,
对于不变存储，你不更新，
you can actually stick the hash of the file in there,
你可以把文件的哈希值放在那里，
but for mutable storage, you know that's going to see a lot of writes,
但对于可变存储，将会看到大量写入，
you shouldn't do that, you should use this key.
你不应该那样做，你应该用这个密钥。
I see, and then how is it possible to validate
我明白了，那么如何确认
with mutable storage that you're getting the right data, then.
使用可变存储，你获得了正确的数据。
Yeah, so presumably a very good question,
是的，这是一个非常好的问题，
well, you can validate,
好的，你可以验证，
whether you actually obtain and actually was produced by x,
你是否得到了，是否是由 x 产生的，
because you have the public key for x,
因为你有 x 的公钥，
and you can verify what actually the signature on the todo file,
你可以验证 todo 文件上的签名，
indeed checks out with the public key of x,
用 x 的公钥进行验证，
so you at least know that x has written it, right,
所以你至少知道是 x 写的，
you may not know this most recent version,
你可能不知道这个最新版本，
and so the paper sort of, they don't talk about these are you know in detail,
所以论文没有详细地讨论这些，
the basic system,
在基本系统中，
we probably have to stick version numbers in it,
我们可能必须在其中插入版本号，
and so at least you can detect rollback,
至少你可以检测到回滚，
there's a little trick,
这有点困难，
actually I don't know how to how to actually,
我也不知道该怎么做，
you can't really be sure that you actually got the latest version.
你不能确定你得到了最新的版本。
But to where the modifications to a mutable storage coming into?
但是对可变存储的修改来自哪里？
Your todo file is here,
你的 todo 文件在这里，
like in here, like todo file,
比如这里， todo 文件，
and if an application,
如果一个应用程序，
might todo list application want to update todo file,
可能是 todo 列表应用程序想要更新 todo 文件，
just goes ahead and does it,
只管去做就行了，
and, and then signs it using the public key,
然后使用公钥对其进行签名，
and sticks it in the, and sticks in for the given URI.
并将其给指定的 URI 。
And would that be done through the routing layer as well,
这是否也通过路由层来完成，
because you want to find where in the storage.
因为你想找出存储在什么地方。
Yeah, so user 2 will retrieve x's zonefile, right,
是的，所以用户 2 将获取 x 的 zonefile ，
and once it has x's zonefile,
一旦它有了 x 的 zonefile ，
it knows where the file, the todo file is,
它知道 todo 文件的位置，
because there's the URI sits in the zonefile.
因为这里有 URI 在 zonefile 中。
So again, they could retrieve it and a check the signature.
再次，他们可以取回它并检查签名。
About the URI, are there,
关于这里的 URI ，
it is it only one URI per name in the zonefile, or.
在 zonefile 中，每个名字只有一个 URI 吗？
I don't know, unclear exactly how it works,
我不知道，不清楚它到底是怎么工作的，
I'm sorry, I'm not you know, I need to check out the source code
抱歉，我需要检查一下源代码，
and look at the specific format zonefiles.
并查看特定格式的 zonefile 。
Since we're publishing the public key
由于我们发布公钥
together with all the rest of the data in the zone file,
与 zonefile 中的所有其他数据一起，
doesn't mean I could just make up a private key,
是不是意味着我可以编造一个私钥，
make like matching public key
匹配公钥，
and just stick something in there and say I'm user,
在其中插入一些东西，然后说我是用户，
because, because they do provide public key,
因为它们提供了公钥，
so can I now just lie?
所以我能不能撒谎？
Well, you can't falsify the zone file, correct,
嗯，你不能篡改 zonefile ，
because the zonefile, the hash of the zonefile
因为 zonefile 的哈希值
must match the hash that sits in the blockchain,
必须与区块链中的哈希值匹配，
so only the version that actually entered the blockchain record
所以，只有进入区块链记录的版本
mapping x you know to that hash zonefile,
将 x 映射到哈希 zonefile ，
only that person could have produce that zonefiles.
只有那个人才能产生那个 zonefile 。
I see, thank you.
我明白了，谢谢。
Okay?
好的?
Well, so this is basically the big picture,
好的，所以这是一幅大的图景，
and if you got this, if you got this part,
如果你得到了这个部分，
then basically the rest of sort of details
然后其他一些细节，
and important or maybe less important,
重要或不那么重要的，
this is the key thing to understand.
这是要理解的关键事情。
Okay, there's a couple things I want to go over,
好的，有几件事我想说一下，
I particularly want to talk a little bit more about name creation,
我特别想更多地讨论一下名字创造，
because there's a couple little details, that are actually interesting.
因为有几个小细节，很有趣。
So turns out name creation actually has two part to it,
命名有两个部分，
the first of all, the user needs to have of course some Bitcoins,
首先，用户当然需要一些比特币，
because you gotta pay,
因为你需要支付，
the reason you have to have some Bitcoins,
你必须拥有一些比特币的原因是，
because you gotta convince one of the miners
因为你必须说服其中一个矿工
to actually include your transaction in the Bitcoin ledger.
将你的交易纳入比特币账本。
And so it turns out there are two transactions for every name that you create,
所以你创建的每个名字都有两笔交易，
and one is a basically a pre-order transaction,
一种是预购交易，
and in the pre-order transaction,
在预购交易中，
you don't really list the name,
你不会把名字列出来，
but actually the hash of the name,
而是名字的哈希值，
so, anybody who receives the pre-order transaction,
所以，任何收到预购交易的人，
doesn't know what the name is,
不知道名字是什么，
but you know does know what the hash with the name is.
但是知道这个名字的哈希值是什么。
And then there's the second transaction really registers the name,
然后是第二个交易真正注册名字，
and that basically contains the actual name,
它包含了实际的名字，
which we first published the hash, the hash of the zonefile.
我们首先发布 zonefile 的哈希值。
And so why, why, why is this done,
那么为什么要这样做，
this is actually something that Namecoin did,
这实际上是 Namecoin 所做的，
and they adopted from Namecoin here,
他们在这里采用 Namecoin ，
why do it in this way?
为什么要这样做？
Because if you directly announce the name,
因为如果你直接宣布名字，
then someone else can raise you
然后其他人可以[]你，
and try to register that name before you.
并尝试在你之前注册这个名字。
Yeah, this is a common problems go from front problem.
是的，这是一个常见的问题，从前面开始的问题。
Oops, there we go again, sorry.
糟糕，又来了，抱歉。
So front runner problem exactly describe,
所以领跑者问题准确地描述了，
let's say you're trying to register google.com,
假设你尝试注册 google.com ，
and somebody sees you doing that,
如果有人看到你这么做，
of course you submit a transaction, correct,
你当然会提交一笔交易，
not in the blockchain yet,
还没有进入区块链，
for example a miner might actually see
例如，一个矿工看到，
or somebody else that actually sits in the Bitcoin network,
或者其他在比特币网络中的人，
and decide going to running ahead
并决定领先，
and trying to get my transaction
并试图获得我的交易，
to claiming you know google.com into the Bitcoin before you,
在你之前，声称 google.com 进入比特币，
and now then I own google.com,
现在我拥有 google.com ，
and so to avoid that problem,
所以，为了避免这个问题，
you first actually have to enter the hash into the Bitcoin chain,
你首先必须将哈希值输入比特币链中，
then you wait a while to make sure that the,
然后你等待一段时间以确保，
that that record sits in the Bitcoin blockchain,
这一记录位于比特币区块链中，
you know have six whatever ten blocks
你有六个或十个区块，
and then after that you sure,
然后，在你确定之后，
like you burn the name in the, as they call in the blockchain,
你将名字刻在区块链中，
at that point you actually do the actual registration.
在这一点上，你进行真正的注册。
I've got a question regarding that.
关于这一点，我有一个问题。
So what, what,
所以，什么，
why is it not possible for an attacker
为什么攻击者不可能
to say pre-compute [] with the hash of google.com,
预先计算 google.com 的哈希值，
and then look through the blockchain,
然后查看区块链，
and see if someone posted a hash of google.
看看有没有人发布了 google 的哈希值。
Yeah, yeah absolutely,
是的，绝对是，
yeah, so absolutely you know there's slightly more sophisticated than this,
是的，所以绝对比这个稍微复杂一点，
you know just purely hash,
只是纯粹的哈希，
presumably a bunch of other arguments that go into,
还有很多参数进入，
it including a nonce or something,
它包括 nonce 或其他东西，
otherwise, you could make a dictionary, right.
否则，你可以创建一个字典。
In some ways, this is really not their invention,
在某些方面，这不是他们的发明，
but as I said before,
就像我之前说的，
it came out of, came out of a Namecoin.
它来自于 Namecoin 。
Okay, so let's you know go back to the sort of collaborative apps,
好的，让我们回到协作应用程序，
for collaborative, collaborative decentralized applications.
对于协作性去中心化的应用程序。
So just go back to our todo list as an example,
以我们的 todo 列表为例，
and just to see you know how it really would work,
看看它到底是怎么工作的，
you know so sketch out again, how it would work,
所以再次勾勒出来，它是如何工作的，
so basically with two users, correct,
所以有两个用户，
running you know the todo list app,
运行 todo 列表应用程序，
here U1, here U2,
这里是 U1 ，这里是 U2 ，
and they basically exchanged some information with each other,
它们互相交换了一些信息，
basically saying are in some way,
使用某种方法，
U1 has learned about U2's name,
U1 已经知道了 U2 的名字，
and U2 has learned about U1's name.
U2 也知道了 U1 的名字。
And then sort of that step, of course has to happen,
当然，这一步必须要发生，
it has to happen securely,
它必须安全地发生，
in the sense, that U1 really need to know that actually is U2's name,
U1 需要知道 U2 的名字，
then they can,
然后它们可以，
U1, U1 can look up U2's name,
U1 可以查询 U2 的名字，
you know get its zonefile for that,
获取它的 zonefile ，
find the entry for say the todo list in the zonefile,
在 zonefile 中找到 todo 列表条目，
you know zonefile also contains you know the public key,
zonefile 也包含公钥，
and this might be not,
这可能不是，
like you know U2 might have many public keys, private keys,
U2 可能有许多公钥、私钥，
because you probably don't want to have one master private key,
因为你可能不想拥有一个主私钥，
that you use for everything,
用在所有地方，
because if you use that one master private key
因为如果你使用那个主私钥，
or somebody still you're in bad shape,
或者一些人是不好的，
so typically I think in a block, in blockchain,
所以，通常我认为在区块链中，
there should have a private key per application.
每个应用程序都应该有一个私钥。
So you know U1 basically look at U2's name, looks up in zonefile,
所以， U1 在 zonefile 中查找 U2 的名字，
but todo list public key and URI
以及 todo 列表公钥和 URI ，
you know through the Blockstack file system,
通过 Blockstack 文件系统，
which tracks away the different storage providers,
它跟踪不同的存储提供商，
and actually retrieve you know the actual name, the actual file,
并获取实际名称、实际文件，
you know check the signature on the file,
检查文件上的签名，
maybe version numbers,
也许是版本号，
and and then basically use that to construct you know the todo list from U2,
然后用它来构建 U2 中的 todo 列表，
and worked out with U1's,
并与 U1 的一起起作用，
and similarly you know you basically U2 is exactly the same way thing,
同样地， U2 也是一样的方式，
you know as U1's name,
U1 的名字，
and [] goes off and you know which is U1's todo list,
然后继续，是 U1 的 todo 列表，
and you know that way, they can have a collaborative application,
通过这种方式，他们可以拥有一个协作应用程序，
and so for example when U2 updates its file,
所以，当 U2 更新它的文件时，
then, you know periodically U1's app you know goes
然后， U1 的应用程序定期，
and retrieves the new, retrieves the todo list,
获取新的 todo 列表，
and just see if there are any updates.
看看有没有什么更新。
Does this sort of makes sense?
这能理解吗？
You see here,
你看这里，
I think there's like one of these central points of decentralized applications,
我认为这是去中心化应用程序的中心点之一，
this applications is building you know quite a different way,
这种应用程序构建使用一种很不同的方式，
than the ones that we're talking about very early on, correct,
而不是我们之前谈到的，
if we go back to this picture of the centralized site,
如果我们回到这张集中式站点的图片，
that we're building a todo list application, correct,
我们构建了一个 todo 列表应用程序，
in the database, have the U1's todo list and U2's todo list,
在数据库中，有 U1 的 todo 列表和 U2 的 todo 列表，
and yeah you know like the todo list app,
以及 todo 列表应用程序，
you know basically you know retrieve these the content todo list
获取这些 todo 列表的内容，
with a simple SQL query,
使用一个简单的 SQL 查询，
and you know put them together, actually presented to the user,
然后把它们放在一起，呈现给用户，
when we see that in this decentralized scheme,
当我们看到在这个去中心化的方案中，
and it was quite a bit more mechanism involved,
这涉及到更多的机制，
to actually make this happen,
才能实现这一点，
and in the program,
在程序中，
it doesn't really have the same easy SQL interface as the centralized case.
它没有与集中式案例相同的简单的 SQL 接口。
So I think this is one of sort of maybe the sticking points
所以我认为这可能是症结之一，
with these decentralized applications,
这些去中心化应用程序，
how can you make them as easy to write as decentralized versions.
如何才能简单编写去中心化版本。
Okay, so I want to leave some time this time around,
好的，我想留点时间，
instead of do breakout rooms,
进行分组会议室，
leave some time around time for questions or discussion,
留下一些时间提问或讨论，
but since this is a little bit more of sort of provoking type exercise,
但因为这是一种更发人深省的练习，
than an exercise in,
比起一个练习，
well, here's a hard technical problem,
这是一个棘手的技术问题，
here's the right solution,
这是正确的解决方案，
here's learn the right solution,
这是了解正确解决方案，
and then use it.
然后使用它。
So, you know just want to hear people's opinion or questions
所以，想听听人们的意见或问题，
about any aspect of these decentralized applications versus centralized,
关于这些去中心化应用程序与中心化应用程序的任何方面，
then or the particular design for Blockstack or any other issue,
然后是 Blockstack 的设计或任何其他问题，
and we can debate it together.
我们可以一起讨论。
Wait, so what's the main difficulty in,
等等，最大的困难是什么，
instead of using like a file system API to use like a relational database?
使用文件系统 API 而不是使用关系数据库？
Well, how do you write,
好的，你怎么写，
how do you present the world wide relational database,
你怎么呈现全球关系数据库，
all these user files,
所有这些用户文件，
all these files will be different users,
所有这些文件将是不同的用户，
live in all kinds of different storage providers,
在各种不同的存储提供商中，
and you know you can't like do whatever,
你不能做任何事，
you can't do select across all the storage providers,
你不能在所有存储提供商之间进行 select ，
that be crazy,
这太疯狂了，
you couldn't also download all the user data to your computer,
你也不能把所有的用户数据下载到你的计算机上，
because that would be too expensive.
因为那太昂贵了。
What about like, like a linked data database?
关联数据库，会怎么样？
I think this is [] researcher actually to pursue, right,
我想这是[]研究人员要去追求的，
but you could actually built sort of scalable database infrastructure,
但你可以构建一种可伸缩的数据库基础设施，
where users still control their own data having different locations again,
其中用户仍然控制位于不同位置的自己的数据，
and provide sort of relational data type interface,
并提供一种关系型数据类型接口，
certainly Blockstack Blockstack doesn't offer to you.
显然， Blockstack 不能提供给你。
Yes, another question is,
是的，另一个问题是，
like what are the benefits of this decentralized PKI versus like web of trust PKI,
这种去中心化的 PKI 与信任网络 PKI 相比有什么好处，
which I guess is also decentralized.
我想它也是去中心化的。
Yeah, so other, maybe some points here, correct,
是的，所以其他，也许是这里的一些要点，
you know there's other Web of trust PKI,
还有其他信任网络 PKI ，
Web of trust PKIs,
信任网络 PKI ，
you know, I mean the one, I'm most familiar with is is Keybase,
我最熟悉的是 Keybase ，
I think we should mention a couple of times before,
我想我们在之前提到过几次，
and you know Keybase actually we haven't talked to this in great detail,
Keybase ，我们没有详细讨论过这个，
but one of the things that's also challenging these kind of systems,
但是，同样挑战这类系统的一件事是，
is like how do you represent groups of users,
你如何表示用户组，
like we saw a little bit in the SUNDR paper,
比如我们在 SUNDR 的论文中看到的，
where gonna have group names, public keys for the group names,
有组名，组名的公钥，
and how to create them and manage them and actually stick them in,
如何创建和管理它们，如何将它们插入其中，
how do you incorporate those in a in the chain of records, name records,
如何将这些合并到名称记录链中，
and Keybase is really really fought out story for that,
Keybase 是一个为此而战的故事，
and you know actually a very impressive probably you know the truth,
非常令人印象深刻的真相，
probably, probably considered the best sort of decentralized you know PKI out there,
可能是最好的去中心化的 PKI ，
and the most thought out,
最深思熟虑的是，
they're probably most widely used.
它们可能是使用最广泛的。
So are there any benefits of doing it of like Blockstack method,
那么像 Blockstack 这样做有什么好处吗，
or is it just more extensible?
或者它只是更具可扩展性？
Well, one of the things that actually Blockstack get correct is,
好的， Blockstack 得到的一件事情是，
is this uniqueness properties,
是这个唯一的特性，
because the Web of trust, there's basically not a global naming system,
因为信任网络，没有一个全球命名系统，
you know like you know it is like my todo list or my contact list,
比如我的 todo 列表或者我的联系人列表，
and you know whatever who I name,
不管怎么命名，
if I have a name John for some particular public key, that is my John,
如果我对某个公钥有一个名字 John ，那就是我的 John ，
and if I sent John to you is like string John,
如果发送 John 给你，比如字符串 John ，
and it probably resolve different differently in your contact list than mine.
它在你的联系人列表中的解析可能与我的不同。
So, in fact, so Keybase much more is decentralized,
所以，事实上， Keybase 更多是去中心化的，
but it doesn't really go for these global unique names,
但它并不适用于全球唯一的名称，
this case, that you know Keybase once in a while publishes,
这种情况下， Keybase 偶尔发布，
the hash of all the names,
所有名称的哈希，
of the complete Merkle tree of all names in in blockchain too,
以及区块链中所有名称的完整的 Merkle 树，
so you can verify what the Keybase actually is not playing the games,
这样你可以确认 Keybase 不是玩那个游戏，
but you know, it's much more,
但是，还有更多，
it doesn't really have globally unique names.
它没有全球唯一的名称。
Sorry, just a clarification question,
抱歉，我只想确认一个问题，
earlier on in the lecture,
在课程的前面部分，
you mentioned how users have the,
你提到了用户如何拥有，
basically they can choose who to show their data to
他们可以选择向谁显示他们的数据，
or who they give access to their data to,
或者他们允许谁访问他们的数据，
but I'm not quite sure I see,
但我不太确定我看到了，
how that's implemented within that system.
这是如何在那个系统中实现的。
Yeah, there are the way,
好的，这里有方法，
one way to do it
有一种做的方法，
and I don't know exactly what to Blockstack that does is,
我不确定 Blockstack 是怎么做的，
that you encrypt the same data for different users,
你为不同的用户加密相同的数据，
so if you wanna share your data only with user 1 or user 2,
如果你只想与用户 1 或用户 2 共享数据，
then, you encrypt you know with the public keys of user 1 user 2,
然后，你使用用户 1 和用户 2 的公钥进行加密，
and then those are the only two that can decrypt it,
然后只有这两个可以解密它，
and so that gives you access control lists.
这就为你提供了访问控制表。
I see, so you'd have to for each person you wanted to give the data to,
我明白了，所以对于每个你想要提供数据的人，
you have to encrypt it with their public key.
你必须用他们的公钥对其加密。
And you can get more sophisticated about this,
你可以在这方面变得更复杂，
you know you can actually have group keys,
你可以拥有组密钥，
and you know give a group of users you know actually have a lock box,
给一组用户一个秘钥，
that has a group key in it,
其中包含组密钥，
and you increase the lock box with the different users you know public keys,
使用不同用户的公钥增加密钥盒，
and then they get access to that lock box,
然后他们访问那个密钥盒，
they get the key out of it,
他们从里面拿到了密钥，
and then they can decrypt the key,
然后他们可以对密钥解密，
so you only have to encrypt the data only once instead of multiple times,
所以，你只需对数据加密一次，而不是多次，
and you have to decrypt, the encrypt lock box multiple times.
你必须对密钥盒加密多次。
Thank you.
谢谢。
That would be down at the level of the content of the zonefile, right?
这将降低 zonefile 的内容级别，对吗？
Yeah, presumably
是的，可能是，
or may be the key that zonefiles you know the key for the lock box, if you will,
或者 zonefile 的密钥是密钥盒的，
and again I'm not actually a hundred percent sure exactly
同样，我不是百分之百确定
how Blockstack Blockstack file system does actually control,
Blockstack 文件系统如何控制，
what it does it all,
它所做的一切，
but other people have done these kinds of designs.
但其他人做过这样的设计。
Do you think system like this be able to compete with like the centralized model
你认为这样的系统能够与集中式模式竞争吗，
in terms of performance or scalability,
在性能或可伸缩性方面，
and what would it take.
那要付出什么代价。
I, I don't know, good question,
我不知道，好问题，
I don't really know the answer,
我不知道答案，
it's the case, correct,
它是这种情况，
like even the simplest size is not that easy to scale,
即使最简单的规模也不是那么容易扩展的，
you know we've read quite a number of papers, right
我们已经读了相当多的论文，
to see how, how to make them scale between millions of users,
了解如何让它们在数百万用户之间进行扩展，
and so you know both,
所以你知道两个，
it's getting anything to a large large number of users is not easy,
要让大量的用户获得任何东西并不容易，
and certainly in the case with decentralized apps,
当然，在去中心化应用程序的情况下，
not gonna be easy either,
这也不容易，
but on the other hand, like if there's not by sharing,
但另一方面，如果不是通过共享，
like the user 1 actually only have to share to do 10 other users,
比如用户 1 只需要分享给其他 10 个用户，
that's probably not be a big issue, correct,
这可能不是什么大问题，
in some ways, you can think about the decentralized architecture
在某些方面，你可以认为去中心化的体系结构
is basically sharded by user,
是按用户划分的，
and each app you know runs in one of user's computers,
每个应用程序都在用户的一台计算机上运行，
so you don't need maybe data centers of caches,
所以，你不需要数据中心的缓存，
so I don't know what the answer to that question actually is,
所以我不知道这个问题的答案是什么，
I will not be able to give you a definitely answer.
我不能给你一个确定的答案。
It's clearly the case that people have demonstrated
很明显，人们已经证明了
bigger scalability of those centralized designs,
这些集中式设计具有更大的可扩展性，
at least so far, we've seen in the decentralized once,
至少到目前为止，我们看到去中心化的一次，
but one reason of that of course is
但其中一个原因当然是
that the centralized designs are widely used,
集中式设计被广泛使用，
the most popular, the most deployed cases.
最受欢迎，部署最多的案例。
I think the, to me the decentralized design is just intriguing design,
我想，对我来说，去中心化设计是有趣的设计，
and that it could make to work,
而且可以让它发挥作用，
you know it would be pretty cool.
这会很酷。
Any other thoughts that people might have for, or like to argue about?
大家还有什么想法，或想讨论的？
I still feel like the storage aspect is,
我仍然觉得在存储方面是，
like the thing that that William was pointing out,
就像 William 指出的那样，
where like you maybe have an immutable file, that's the the user information,
比如你可能有一个不变的文件，它是用户信息，
but the mutable file that you have somewhere else,
但是你在其他地方拥有的可变文件，
is like a huge problem,
这是个大问题吗，
in so much that,
在这种情况下，
like I I don't really understand,
我真的不明白，
how you can assure redundancy
如何确保冗余，
for a large amount of mutable storage that you might have.
对于你可能拥有的大量可变存储。
Yeah, I think the answer the redundancy maybe not that tough,
是的，我认为冗余的答案可能不是那么困难，
and I think the user is responsible for redundancy,
我认为用户对冗余负责，
so if you like to use, you own it todo list file,
所以，如果你拥有 todo 列表文件，
and your job to replicate it you know multiple times,
你的工作是多次复制它，
so the Blockstack storage servers do that for you,
所以 Blockstack 服务器可以为你做到这一点，
but you got to arrange you know basically for space
但你必须安排空间
and a different storage providers to do that.
和不同的存储提供商来做到这一点。
And so I think in the paper,
所以我认为在论文中，
they talk about like,
他们谈论的是，
oh you replicated that maybe Google Drive and S3,
你可能复制到 Google Drive 和 S3 ，
and presumably S3 internally does its own replication, right,
可能 S3 内部也有自己的复制，
so hopefully you know maybe just actually thought only S3,
所以希望，也许只考虑 S3 ，
and it should be pretty reliable,
它应该是相当可靠的，
probably more reliable than storing data on your SSD, in your laptop.
可能比将数据存储在固态硬盘上更可靠，在你的笔记本电脑上。
The zonefiles are small,
zonefile 很小，
so they're just widely replicated,
所以它们被广泛复制，
and you don't have to trust the storage provider.
你不必信任存储提供商。
Any other thoughts?
还有其他想法吗？
I was thinking it's a little bit wasteful,
我在想，这有点浪费，
that you have in order to register a name,
为了注册一个名字，
and to use this name system, you have to pay,
要使用这个名字系统，你必须付费，
yeah, so I was thinking obviously on a blockchain based system,
是的，所以我是在考虑基于区块链的系统，
you have to incentivize the miners,
你必须激励矿工，
but maybe there's a different cheaper way.
但也许还有一种不同的更便宜的方式。
Yeah, yeah, I I'm not sure,
是的，我不确定，
it seems in some way, that sort of the currency,
在某种程度上，它是一种货币，
and this is sort of very [],
这在某种程度上是非常[]的，
so a reason, exactly for the reason you mentioned,
因为你提到的原因，
because you have miners and you have to incentivize them,
因为你有矿工，你必须激励他们，
I think in general with these transactions are pretty cheap,
我认为总的来说，这些交易都很便宜，
you know basically you know you have to just pay enough, correct,
你只需要付足够的钱，
the miners willing to include your transaction,
矿工们愿意把你的交易包括在内，
and you know today,
你知道，在今天，
you also pay for if you want to register a name in in DNS,
如果你想在 DNS 中注册一个名字，你也需要付费，
you know actually quite a bit of money, not free,
是相当多的钱，不是免费的，
I don't know exactly how economics would work out,
我不知道经济学到底会如何运作，
but the obviously clear that,
但很明显，
this is actually a much more expensive way of doing it,
这是一种成本更高的方式，
other than maybe you burning the planet within electricity,
除了也许你用电力燃烧地球之外，
at least in the Bitcoin case,
至少在比特币的例子中。
but maybe you should use a one of the stake-of-work ledgers,
也许你应该使用一个权益工作账本，
instead of the,
而不是，
okay, proof-of-stake instead of these proof-of-work ledgers.
好的，权益证明而不是工作量证明账本。
It will be possible just to swap it out, in place of.
把它替换掉是可能的，替换。
I think I think this is what the papers argue, correct,
我想这是论文所讨论的，
their particular design is really not very dependent on the underlying blockchain,
他们的设计不是很依赖于底层的区块链，
and they could easily switch to another blockchain,
他们可以很容易地切换到另一个区块链，
in fact this is the second blockchain that worked out, correct,
事实上，这是第二个工作的区块链，
they first use Namecoin and then they switch to Bitcoin,
他们首先使用 Namecoin ，然后改用比特币，
and I think the argument in the paper is
我认为论文中的论点是，
making we could actually switch to another blockchain, we wanted to.
我们可以切换到另一个我们想使用的区块链。
What in particular is stored in the name history?
名字历史中具体存储了什么？
In the,
在,
sorry, what, what's the question really?
抱歉，问题到底是什么？
Oh, sorry, the name history in the Blockstack database.
哦，抱歉， Blockstack 数据库中的名字历史记录。
Yeah, this, this,
是的，这个，
yeah I don't really mean like these three different guys.
是的，我不是说这三个。
Yeah.
是的。
Different versions of the zonefile.
zonefile 的不同版本。
Oh, so just like version numbers.
哦，所以就像版本号一样。
Yeah, I think so, I'm not hundred percent sure,
是的，我想是的，我不是百分之百确定，
but the,
但是，
but like these correspond to the three updates to the zonefile, correct,
但这些对应于 zonefile 的三个更新，
here's number one, here's number two,
这是第一个，这是第二个，
maybe they keep using version of zonefile around.
也许他们继续使用 zonefile 的版本。
Any other topics that people want to bring up?
大家还想提出其他什么话题吗？
Okay, so we end the sort of time anyway,
好的，我们要结束这段时间，
okay, so let's say why don't we stop here,
好的，让我们在这里停止，
so people need to need to leave can leave,
所以人们需要离开就离开，
and I'll see hopefully everybody on Thursday,
我希望周四能见到大家，
I'm going to see eight, we have eight design, eight projects,
我要去看八个，我们有八个设计，八个项目，
and so the eight teams will present the on Thursday what they've done,
八个团队将在周四展示他们所做的，
instead of lab lab 4,
而不是实验 4 ，
and it should be and the the projects quite cool and interesting,
项目非常酷和有趣，
so hopefully you will be entertained,
所以希望你能从中得到乐趣，
and that makes concludes this lecture,
这就是这节课的总结，
hopefully a bit of goal is a little bit [],
希望一点，目标就是一点[]，
and you know sort of talk about designs, decentralized designs,
讨论了去中心化设计，
to the has, that's probably the user on their data,
可能是用户在他们的数据上，
and you know and we look in the context of Blockstack,
我们看了 Blockstack ，
at least one particular design,
至少一个特定的设计，
how they did naming in a way,
他们是如何以某种方式命名的，
that gives global names, unique names, and human readable,
给出了全球名称，唯一名称和人类可读，
okay?
好的？
So that's the end of this lecture,
这节课到此结束，
and then hopefully see you on Thursday,
希望周四能见到你，
which is going to be our final class meeting.
将是我们最后一次课程。
And if you have any questions, please feel free to stick around,
如果你有任何问题，请随时留下来，
you can talk.
你可以谈论。
Professor, for presentation,
教授，对于演示，
are we supposed to do something more of a demo,
我们是不是做一些更多的演示，
or should we have slides prepared or combination both.
或者我们应该准备幻灯片，或者两者都有。
Yeah, we post some instructions,
是的，我们贴了一些说明，
you're pretty free to do so, what you wanna do,
你可以自由地去做你想做的，
you know the things you want to do is to convince you know the class,
你想做的是说服全班同学，
you know what [] did and why is cool,
做了什么，为什么很酷，
show demo is a good idea,
演示 demo 是个好主意，
you don't have a ton of time,
你的时间不多，
so I think the typical thing to do is,
所以我认为最典型的做法是，
people have a few slides for explaining what they did,
人们有几张幻灯片来解释他们所做的，
and then maybe cook demos
然后可能还会制作 demo ，
to see how it actually materialized.
看看它是如何实现的。
Great, okay, thanks.
好的，好的，谢谢。
Yeah, we don't expect you to
是的，我们不指望你，
whatever in hours preparing for this, correct,
在几个小时内为这个做准备，
do we try to share what you've done.
试着分享你所做的。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
I just wanted to ask,
我只想问一下，
so it's like what is the reasoning behind,
所以这是什么原因，
just having just using the same Bitcoin the blockchain,
使用比特币相同的区块链，
and just putting the, the transactions for the naming on there,
把命名的交易记录放在那里，
together with all the rest of the things, right.
再加上其他所有的东西。
I I think these are the papers,
我想这些论文，
so they started out building on top of Namecoin,
他们开始在 Namecoin 上构建，
which is a special purpose ledger for naming,
这是一种用于命名的特殊用途的账本，
and, and they discovered basically the,
他们发现了，
[], what the security issues with namecoin,
Namecoin 的安全问题，
one of them being actually not many miners,
其中一个是矿工并不多，
so, it observes that basically there are miner pools
它观察到有一些矿工池，
and basically have more than 50% of the capacity, and work capacity,
有 50% 以上的工作容量，
therefore you could do anything they wanted to do,
因此可以做他们想做的任何事情，
to the principle to the ledger,
到账本上，
and so they wanted ton sit on a blockchain that is widely used very popular,
所以他们在被广泛使用的区块链上，
and not easy to overtake by the adversary.
不容易被对手超越。
Okay, I remember the 51% yeah, remember.
好的，我记得那 51% 。
Okay, makes sense.
好的，理解了。
And I also wanted to ask about,
我还想问一下，
the URIs, there URIs to, to the zonefile storage system
zonefile 存储系统的 URI ，
not just like S3 something something, right.
不是 S3 之类的东西。
There could be,
可能会是，
the problem is something a little bit more general,
问题可能更普遍，
because it's actually interpreted by by Blockstack file system,
因为它是由 Blockstack 文件系统解释的，
so and the Blockstack file system has backends for the different storage provider,
Blockstack 文件系统有用于不同存储提供商的后端，
where S3 or Google Drive or whatever,
不管是 S3 还是 Google Drive 还是什么，
and so there's some naming schemes,
所以有一些命名方案，
the Blockstack file system can interpret,
Blockstack 文件系统可以解释，
and then figure out how to retrieve the right file from the the correct backend.
然后找出如何从正确的后端检索正确的文件。
This is just to make them the same.
这只是为了让它们变得一样。
Yeah, excally, usually an application writer doesn't really want doesn't care,
是的，没错，通常应用程序编写者并不在乎，
whether it's stored S3 or Google Drive,
无论是存储的 S3 还是 Google Drive ，
or we should you where [] have to deal with that.
或者[]必须处理这个。
Thank you so much.
非常感谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
I had a question about
我有一个问题，
why Zooko's triangle is kind of like,
为什么 Zooko 三角是，
I think that people think about a lot like,
我认为人们想的很多，
it seems that you can have a client side interpret the human non meaningful data,
似乎你可以有一个客户端来解释人类没有意义的数据，
that you can make kind of all the data human meaningful,
你可以让所有的数据对人类有意义，
on the client side to the to the user,
在客户端侧到用户，
and so I wasn't completely sure like what,
所以我不能完全确定，
like what the innovation here is
这里的创新之处是什么，
or why people, why this is a trade off.
或者为什么这是一种权衡。
Yeah, well, I guess this is the best slide, I can give you,
是的，我想这是，我能给你的最好的幻灯片，
were I can give you a whole bunch of naming examples,
我能给你举一大堆命名的例子，
basically two of three, but not all three,
三个中的两个，但不是所有的三个，
and sort of for example like you know,
例如，
the you know we talked about Keybase, correct,
我们讨论过 Keybase ，
decentralized, you knew over not unique,
去中心化的，不是唯一的，
and now you're gonna argue,
现在你会争论，
when it's that important to have globally unique names,
什么时候拥有全球唯一的名称很重要，
it's like whatever it's a globally unique name,
一个全球唯一的名字，
like 6.824 what does it mean,
比如 6.824 是什么意思，
and who's associated with it,
以及与之相关的人，
so if you're coming from that angle,
所以如果你是从那个角度来看，
I think that's a very valid question.
我认为这是一个非常合理的问题。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So one of the things that has always kind of bothered me,
有一件事一直困扰着我，
when we're reading through these blockchain type of papers is,
当我们读这些区块链类型的论文时，
like what happens in a hundred years,
比如一百年后会发生什么，
when the ledger gets to like multiple tera,
当账本得到数万亿，
I don't know if, yeah like multiple terabytes or something.
数万亿字节或什么东西。
Yeah.
嗯。
Do we not, do we not having escape plan,
我们是不是没有避免方案，
like what's gonna happen then?
接下来会发生什么？
I don't know,
我不知道，
hard to speculate on the hundred years out into the future,
很难推测未来的一百年，
I presume, what would you do,
我想，你可以做的，
so you put a checkpoint in the,
所以你设置一个检查点，
yeah, I can imagine multiple schemes for getting out of this,
是的，我能想象出多种摆脱困境的方案，
one you could make a checkpoint of the state,
一个你可以在状态设置一个检查点，
you know build on the ledger,
建立在账本上，
and include the hash that checkpoint into the ledger,
并将检查点的哈希值包括到帐本中，
and then as long as you can replicate the checkpoint widely,
然后，只要你可以广泛复制检查点，
and then you can basically start running from the checkpoint
然后你可以从检查点开始运行，
to cut out the beginning,
截去开头的部分，
this is like like you were doing in lab,
这与你在实验中做的一样，
you know Raft doing, correct.
Raft 所做的。
Would the party that does that have to be trusted or?
这样做的一方是必须得到信任还是？
What we did,
我们所做的，
presumably client 1 go have to go along,
想必客户 1 必须跟着走，
and realize that they should get that checkpoint,
意识到他们到达那个检查点，
you'll be able to construct you know the current state of the world,
你将能够构建世界的当前状态，
so I presume that which requires some critical changes, probably some fork.
我假设这需要一些关键的改变，可能需要一些分叉。
This is not a huge issue, correct,
这不是什么大问题，
usually the rate of Bitcoin,
通常比特币的汇率，
because like you know the number of transactions
因为交易数量，
for seconds you can do is actually small,
每秒钟你可以做的很少，
like if you remember from the Bitcoin paper,
如果你还记得比特币论文上的内容，
there's some calculation like you know what the total size would be,
有一些计算，比如总的大小是多少，
if you do this,
如果你这样做，
furthermore and you remember correctly from the Bitcoin paper,
另外，你还记得在比特币论文上，
there's a bunch of optimizations,
有很多优化，
where you don't really have to remember every transaction for every coin,
你不必记住每一枚币的每一笔交易，
you basically have to remember the last transaction for every coin,
你必须记住每一枚币的最后一笔交易，
and you could do that
你可以这样做，
by just remembering the block headers instead of the complete block,
只记住区块头而不是完整的区块，
so Bitcoin have sort of a built-in solution to this problem.
所以，比特币对这个问题有某种内置的解决方案。
I see, so the main bottleneck is more or less when new machines come up,
我明白了，所以主要的瓶颈是当新机器出现时，
they need to verify the [],
它们需要验证[]，
but after that, then things are relatively more optimized.
但在那之后，事情就相对更优化了。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Okay, that for today,
好的，这就是今天的，
thank you all, see you Thursday.
谢谢大家，周四见。